hello and welcome this is active guest
stream number 39.1 it's March 16 2023
we are here with shuji Eric elmoz Nino
and Guillaume Dumas we're going to have
a presentation followed by a discussion
section so thank you all for joining and
off to you for the presentation
all right thanks Daniel uh yeah I'm Eric
I'm a PhD student in uh Joshua bengio's
lab I'm shuji I'm a postdoc with Joshua
yeah no we're really excited to be here
thanks for the invite
um we're gonna be talking about why we
can't describe conscious experiences
um so this is this is going to be our
take on on a really long-standing
problem in the philosophy of mind but
we're going to be looking at it through
the lens of computational Neuroscience
and information Theory so uh yeah
hopefully it'll be fun for everyone it
mixes a bunch of disciplines
so I think the the most Salient way to
illustrate the problem that we're going
to be uh addressing is to ask you to try
and think about how you would describe
the experience of seeing the color red
um so probably the kind of stuff that's
going in your head is things like well
it's a bright aggressive color you know
symbolizes love that sort of stuff and
um in a sense this this is the
description
um it's effective I would be able to to
guess which color you were describing uh
but in a in another sense it's really
inadequate right if I were blind for
instance um your description would be
totally useless I would I would be no
better in understanding what red looks
like so there's this real sense in which
conscious experiences are ineffable such
that we can't describe them and this
applies to percepts like red but it also
applies to experiences more broadly like
right the the experience of you know
having a thought is just so ineffable so
hard to describe it
um and really importantly this this
doesn't happen with most of our
knowledge all right I could describe
most of what I know except for
experiences they have this special place
so uh it's a big Topic in the philosophy
of mind
um because it relates a lot to this
thing called the the hard problem of
Consciousness so basically all the hard
problem is it's uh it's the problem of
how and why physical processes give rise
to conscious experiences in the first
place
um so this is probably the the oldest
and most debated problem in the
philosophy of mine and it's even led
many to the conclusion that you know
actually we're going to give up and and
Consciousness can't be explained with
physical theories at all you know that
it it can't simply emerge from
Neuroscience computation or known
physical laws
um so that's that's a bold statement and
I want to get into all the details uh
about what makes the heart problem so
Salient uh but just here's a few here's
a few things
um so first of all
um we could we could logically conceive
of what are called philosophical zombies
uh philosophical zombies uh very
different from Hollywood zombies they're
basically beings that are physically
identical to us they behave exactly like
us in fact they even have the exact same
neural activity that we do
um but they just aren't conscious all
right so similarly instead of these
these alternates uh agents being
unconscious we could also Imagine them
as just experiencing different things
when they're in the same States uh so
for instance it's conceivable at least
that in an alternate universe the same
exact brain mechanisms that produce an
experience of red in this world would
instead produce an experience of green
and the other and that all experiences
would kind of be like flipped in this
way
um so you know intuitively we think that
these these two thought experiments
aren't actually possible in our universe
but even just their logical
conceivability suggests some kind of
explanatory Gap where Consciousness
doesn't seem to neatly emerge from or be
determined by you know physical state or
function
um another really prominent thought
experiment is uh the knowledge argument
and this is the main sort of problem
that our work is going to address we're
not going to address all facets of the
the hard problem of Consciousness but um
this knowledge argument is one of the uh
the biggest arguments against this
against fiscalism
so how the knowledge argument goes is uh
it's another thought experiment it asks
us to imagine
um Mary who has grown up in a black and
white room her whole life uh and you
know this despite this poverty and
stimulus she actually knows uh a lot in
fact we're going to assume that she
knows all the physical facts about how
color perception uh works so all the
relevant physics all the relevant
Neuroscience
Etc
uh and now we're going to ask well does
she learn something new when she steps
out of the room for the first time and
actually experiences color
right and if we say that she does learn
something new which which I think is the
intuitive answer there seems to be a
problem right we assume that she knew
all the relevant physical facts about
color perception so doesn't this mean
that what she learned had to be
something that was non-physical
um and if there was nothing more to
color perception than you know
physically embodied information and
neural activity then the experience is
something describable uh that she
presumably could have read about
understood and would have already known
so it feels like this this thought
experiment really pushes us against uh
physicalism to towards this idea that
maybe you know conscious experience is
has something on top of just information
content
um now of course we don't want to reject
physicalism it's been been very fruitful
for us in the history of science uh so
we really do want to say that experience
just consists of information that can be
described so there has to be something
wrong in this uh this knowledge argument
here
and what we're going to do is we're
going to bite the bullet and acknowledge
that experiences actually are ineffable
so maybe it is the case that experiences
can be described in principle since they
consist of nothing more than information
um but maybe they can't be described uh
in practice or at least they can't be
fully described in practice using
something like language
so then the challenge becomes explaining
why experiences are ineffable under a
physicalist framework
and that's what our work is uh is really
going to be about
okay so the story the structure of the
talk is going to be like this
summarize briefly why uh characterizing
richness and ineffability is an
interesting and important question then
Eric is going to talk about how there's
a natural correspondence between
ineffability and information loss which
is going to let us link biologically
plausible attractor models of working
memory to ineffability essentially
because information loss is inherent in
attractive Dynamics then I will talk
about
um if you consider the ineffability of
conscious experience to verbal report as
just a special case of information lost
between two specific points in the
communication pipeline then you can
actually generalize the notion of
ineffability more broadly by considering
for example loss from sensory processing
to conscious experience and even
interpersonal information loss
um we're going to prove using colgoma of
mutual information that your conscious
experience being ineffable to another
person implies High cognitive
dissimilarity between the two of you
um under our model
and finally we'll talk about
um whether an exact definition of
conscious experience is required at
least for characterizing the nature of
ineffability and richness and also some
open questions
uh so yeah why why is richness and
ineffability an important question
um there are sort of several reasons so
first as as Eric
um said
um understanding Consciousness is not
just of general interest it's a
long-standing central problem in
philosophy of mind
um because it's not easy to reason about
um which has led some Duelists to
believe that Consciousness must be at
least partly non-physical in nature
because they can't see how it could be
explained by physical processes
um but it's also a topic that is of
great interest in machine learning
um because if you assume that
Consciousness is essential to uh human
cognition then it follows that we won't
be able to engineer machines that think
like humans without incorporating
consciousness
um and uh so we're actually going to
argue in this talk that the confusing
aspects of human consciousness such as
its ineffability
um can be understood with information
Theory
um which as you all know is born from
computer science
um we're going to use some
Primitives from from information
um Theory to shed light on why
Consciousness is ineffable and hopefully
to dispel uh some of the Mysteries
surrounding it
all right so uh one of the main
Primitives over here that we're going to
use is
um to to talk about uh attractor
Dynamics uh in the brain an unconscious
experience and how that results in uh
ineffability
so hopefully that this sort of
perspective is uh familiar to most
people but um
we could talk about neurodynamics by
saying the brain has a state at any
particular time and we could denote this
state using a vector so for instance
um in this plot over here you know maybe
we could denote each axis in the state
each Dimension uh using an individual
neuron and maybe uh we denote the the
activity of each neuron using its
average firing rate right so any states
at a particular time would be the firing
rate of all the neurons across the brain
um now there's nothing special about
neurons or firing rates you know if you
think that things like the synapse
strengths or the dendrite potentials or
the astrocytes or whatever else is also
important to the representation you
could include those in the state they're
just additional axes
um the details aren't so important as
long as you know we have some state that
describes uh the what the brain is doing
at any particular time
um now of course the brain is a
dynamical system these states are
changing uh so you can think of of
craping out trajectories through State
space as a function of time
um and the way that uh the the state
evolves will be determined just by the
recurrent connections within the brain
as well as inputs coming from uh
elsewhere maybe we're just talking about
the Dynamics within a given brain region
the inputs would be you know the other
brain regions talking to it
um as well as any sensory stimulus
coming in
right so
this dynamical systems perspective of
the brain it's been really instrumental
in understanding the computations it
performs and one of the primary methods
for characterizing these computations is
to look at what are called uh the state
attractors of the system
and for us as well state attractors are
going to be a really important part of
our ineffability framework in a bit
um so basically what a tractor state is
is as a states where once the system
reaches it it's going to remain there at
least until inputs come in and change
the Dynamics or noise not just the state
out of this attractor
um so you could see this thing clearly
within the figure so so the the X and Y
axis over here are like the state of the
brain again maybe something like the
average firing rates of the neurons
these arrows are illustrating the the
Dynamics of the brain so how the state
will evolve given the brain's
connectivity given the synapses and you
can see that there's some regions where
all the arrows all the Dynamics kind of
contract to a single point
uh so that's called a fixed points if
it's one-dimensional it's a kind of
state attractor and because all the
arrows Point towards it you know once
you finally reach that state you're not
going to move out again until the
Dynamics change because inputs came in
or until noise nudges you out and you
can see that each each state attractor
also is associated with this this sort
of attractive region an attractor Basin
it's called where you know once a
trajectory is somewhere in that region
it will eventually converge to the
attractor and in the absence of noise
um so these These attractors are really
common in the brain uh and also in uh
artificial recurrent neural networks uh
trained on tasks and a big computational
benefit is that they provide a form of
transient memory right once you're in
the attractor you remain there that's
for where the memory comes in uh and
because of this and other benefits
they're implicated in a wide variety of
mineral processes like working memory
long-term memory decision making
um and higher level cognition and we'll
argue Consciousness uh in in general so
they're they're all over the place uh in
the brain
um an additional aspect of them that's
uh interesting and that's going to be
relevant for our talk is that you can
think of attractors as having a sort of
dual discrete and continuous nature
um so what I mean by that is that the
discrete aspect of an attractor is given
by the fact that there's a finite number
of them and that attractors are mutually
exclusive right you're in one or you're
in another
so this means that we could use discrete
symbols to denote which attractor the
system is in right there's a finite
number of them you're either in one or
another and this basically lets us you
know identify or label the states using
a discrete variable
um there's also a notion though in which
an attractor is just a continuous High
dimensional Vector in this this really
high dimensional State space of the
brain right every attractor basically is
just a vector in state space and that
means that they're just not they're not
arbitrarily discrete States they have
continuous representations we can say
for instance that you know one attractor
is more or less similar to another one
depending on how close they are in state
space
um and and that that gives a
representation to the attractor says
that the high dimensional sort of
continuous part
so just to recap the screen part is you
could you could identify which attractor
you're in in the finite set of all
possible attractors
um but you could also uh talk about an
attractor through this like continuous
High dimensional Vector that describes
where the attractor is in the high
dimensional State space of the brain
um and you know to wrap your head around
this there's a a good analogy to word
embeddings in NLP so in NLP you know
each word has a discrete ID that's like
the symbolic discrete part but also each
word is associated to a high dimensional
Vector that gives it a representation
sort of the meaning of the word where we
could say that you know words are more
or less similar uh to each other
okay so we're going to use attractor
Dynamics quite a bit to explain a
significant source of ineffability in
conscious experience later uh but for
that to be relevant I first need to
spend a bit of time to convince you that
neurodynamics that produce conscious
experience uh actually do have
attractors
um and for this there's already a lot of
work in the literature connecting
attractors to conscious experience so
this part is not something uh new from
from our work so for instance
um one of the leading theories of
Consciousness which is the global
workspace Theory actually implicitly
implies uh that attractor Dynamics are
kind of fundamental
uh so what Global workspace Theory says
is basically like across the brain and
all the different regions you have sort
of uh sub-process worker workers uh
basically and these different
distributed mechanisms they can't speak
to each other uh very easily they mainly
communicate through this like Global
workspace it's kind of like a bottleneck
I think of it like a Blackboard uh that
all the different processes across the
brain could write to you could also
think of it as like the ram of the brain
but basically it's collecting
information from the different workers
um and one key uh aspect about uh the
the global workspace it's posited and
the theory is that for content in the
workspace to then be broadcast
to the to the sub processes for instance
for us to be able to
um you know talk about what's in the
workspace for for it to be written to uh
kind of speech regions
the content of the workspace has to be
Amplified and sustained for a certain
amount of time now space stable
basically
and this is clearly where the uh the
attractors come in right attractors by
definition are these states that are
that are stable these states that are
sustained uh so basically what Global
workspace Theory says is that the
context of the global workspace
um that can be used by the rest of the
brain uh are are the attractor States
and the relevance to conscious uh to
Consciousness in this theory is that
um it posits that the contents of This
Global workspace are you know the the
things that we're aware of the things
that we're able to report the things
basically that we're conscious of
um and then just just kind of like
terminologically another term for this
workspace is called uh working memory
um the idea there is it's a sort of like
really short-term memory in the sense
that you could quickly
um you know act on the things that are
in this Global workspace or report on
them they're accessible basically
uh okay so so that's that's one very
powerful argument uh for why attractors
are relevant to Consciousness there's a
bunch of other related arguments uh for
instance just introspectively you could
think of um you know what experience is
like is you know a sequence going from
one thought to the next to the next we
kind of have this like a sequence of
discrete events
um and that that clearly looks like a
dynamical system kind of jumping between
uh attractor States uh and then
experimentally uh there's also been work
showing that in in Psychology
experiments when you sort of uh present
the stimulus to a subject and you vary
the amount of time uh that the stimulus
is presented to kind of bring it below
or above the the conscious threshold
well in the conditions were subject to
report being aware of the stimulus the
main thing that's that's different is
that the representation is really stable
and robust in noise and those are also
clearly properties of uh of attractors
okay so uh again like we'll use those
attractors to identify a source of
ineffability uh in a little bit but
first I need to also introduce how we're
going to formalize the the very notion
of uh ineffability and for this we're
going to use information Theory
um part Shannon information Theory I'll
do that now and then uh she will talk a
bit about comograph complexity as
another formalism
uh but uh hopefully most people are are
familiar with this
um but one thing that we're going to be
using is the entropy of a state uh so
for instance if you have the entropy of
some random variable X to make things
concrete maybe that random variable is
conscious experience so the entropy of
conscious experiences
um that that value would be high if the
distribution over conscious experiences
was kind of a diffuse and flat so
there's equal probability for all
possible experiences and entropy would
be low if the distribution over
conscious experiences was peaky so
that's kind of like the the green
distribution in this image would have
low entropy and the red distribution
that's sort of flatter and more
uncertain would have higher entropy
and um basically what what entropy is
going to quantify in our framework is
the richness of a variable in particular
the richness of conscious experiences
why this is a good measure of richness
is because if conscious experiences
could kind of take on many possible
values with people probability they're
very kind of diverse in that sense well
then it's it's something that's rich
um some other Notions that are going to
be important are mutual information uh
so here that's denoted by um eye of
actin Y and what that denotes is how
much shared information there is between
two random variables uh so again to make
things concrete X we could take to be a
conscious experience whereas why maybe
that's a description of the experience
maybe a verbal description
so in this case the mutual information
will be really high if the verbal
description uniquely determines the um
the experience
so basically another way of saying that
is knowing the verbal description we
have no more uncertainty about what
experience is going on they perfectly
determine each other so that would
maximize the mutual information and in
contrast If the message told you nothing
about the conscious experience and you
were just as unsure as when you didn't
have the message well then the mutual
information would be zero
so this is this is uh useful because we
could use it to define a notion of
ineffability
um so this this conditional uh entropy
that we've written h of x given y uh is
equal basically to the richness of X so
the the entropy of a conscious of
conscious experiences uh minus the
mutual information between conscious
experiences and uh other variables like
their descriptions that's the mutual
information
what this captures basically is how much
information is lost when going from an
experience X to a description y right if
all the information was lost if y
doesn't tell you anything about X the
mutual information is zero and H of X
will uh well the conditional entropy
will be equal to to the richness of x if
y perfectly determined X well then h of
X and the mutual information cancel and
um the conditional entropy would be zero
so what conditional entropy uh describes
basically is how much information is
lost when moving from X so like a
conscious experience to why a
description of it and that's that's a
perfect uh description of what nfability
is intuitively right it's how much
information is is lost when I try and
describe something like an experience
okay so uh I think we have we have uh
most of the uh the background of the way
and now we're ready to uh describe one
main source of ineffability that uh
arises due to attractor Dynamics so very
quickly to describe some some variables
over here that we're going to be using
throughout the presentation if you look
at that top the top right diagram we're
going to have X which is basically the
trajectory of neural activity that's
relevant for a conscious experience so
for instance in global workspace X would
be the trajectory of the working memory
state
uh we're going to assume that that this
uh this this trajectory of neural
activity produces a conscious experience
we're going to be calling that conscious
experience s throughout
but also the trajectory importantly is
going to follow attractor Dynamics right
so they converge the states such as at
so how does this result in ineffability
well basically the idea is that whenever
you have a tractor Dynamics there's a
many-to-one mapping from trajectories to
attractors and this induces information
loss right just knowing the attractor
we're not able to kind of uh go go the
other way around and and infer what the
original trajectory was so that's
there's this conditional entropy this
ineffability of x given a is going to be
high basically
all right why does this matter who cares
if there's information lost between the
trajectory of working memory and the
attractors that it converges to
uh well important thing here again is
that Global workspace postulates that
four working memory contents to be
accessible across the brain it needs to
be Amplified and maintained over a
sufficient duration so it's thought to
be around 100 milliseconds
so this means that you know working
memory is going through these
trajectories X but only a only the
attractor can be reported and only the
attractor could broadly affect behavior
only it could be written to memory only
it could be broadcast to these other
these other processes
so that means that the contents of
working memory uh kind of these
transient contents in the the trajectory
X are inherently fleeting right there's
a rich information that was encoded in
the moment in the moment of the
trajectory but the cat later be recalled
or reported because only the attractors
can be recalled or reported
um and and kind of if we we zoom out and
uh
go back to our philosophical Notions of
ineffability this also explains why it's
difficult to sort of catch yourself in a
thought right working memory encodes
these rich and subtle thoughts through
the trajectory but we can never quite
pinpoints or report in words what those
thoughts consisted of uh were they
verbal were they pre-verbal that they
consist of visual imagery it's really
hard to say exactly and the reasoning
would be that well there's just a lot of
information that's that's lost going
from these trajectories to the
attractors that again we could report on
or that we could recall or they could
just broadly affect Behavior
right so that's one huge source of
ineffability arising from uh attractor
Dynamics in working memory
um now these attractor Dynamics also
give a lower bounds for ineffability
during verbal reports all right so now
at the top right I've added another
variable uh M that's basically some some
verbal message that you could be using
to describe your experience and M is a
function of the attractors right
according to Global workspace only the
attractors can be reported on or used
across the brain
um so this means that
basically
um the the the ineffability of an
experience given a verbal message has to
be at least as great as the ineffability
given an attractor because m is a
function of the attractor
um and and you can't gain information
when applying a function you can only
destroy it
uh but we're actually going to argue
that um the ineffability is not just
lower bounded by the ineffability of the
attractor it's actually uh in practice
quite a bit greater than that and the
reason is that M this message is a
discrete variable right it's language
um whereas a the attractor is this
really high dimensional snapshot of some
cortical States so because of the
asymmetry between the richness of these
variables there has to be uh information
loss and intuitively what's going on
here is that you can think of there as
being a many-to-one mapping from
attractors to messages as well so for
instance if uh I say that I saw Fat Cats
um right that paints a picture but it's
also leaving out significant details
about the original attractor which
presumably encoded things that you were
aware of like the cat's color size
suppose the background all these things
that that you were aware of and that
were encoded in the attractor but you
can't really put into a message without
it being prohibitively uh charge
so again the idea here is that the
ineffability of experiences given
messages higher than given attractors
because the message divides the space of
attractors more coarsely it's it's a
simpler variable it adds additional
information loss
uh so one problem is if if language is
so coarse and simple why can like uh why
can it describe experiences at all
um
and uh the solution is that while
attractors and the message kind of both
share this this uh discrete part
um right so the message uh because uh
language is discrete can be used to
index or identify compositional
attractors uh there's this comparable
richness basically between a message and
a discrete part of the attractor which
means that in practice the richness of
the experience h of s is um is uh
typically much greater than the
ineffability of the experience given
given the message
so that that explains why you know we
still can communicate somewhat with with
language even though it's this really
low dimensional simple thing
all right so to recap quickly uh what we
have over here is the argument says that
detractor Dynamics are empirically
ubiquitous in in neural activity across
brain regions uh they've been proposed
as a computational model for working
memory
um and and prominent models contends
that conscious experience is a
projection of working memory States
uh and one of our key contributions is
to connect these theories to argue that
attractor models working memory offer an
account for the ineffability of
conscious experience because of tractor
Dynamics induced significant information
loss right that's the general argument
um there's there's one quick thing to
add over here so I've been talking about
um you know working memory a lot less
about conscious experience so far uh so
so let's link the two
um the what's going on over here is that
there there's many ways to link
conscious experience to X to working
memory basically uh and and there's kind
of two main options so one is we could
say that the instantaneous state of
working memory is uh always conscious so
all the states in between attractors are
also consciously experienced and uh the
how how attractors would result in um
nfability here is that again what you're
able to recall what you're able to
report is just the attractor not the
actual uh experiences in between
attractors that you were having
but there's another possibility which is
to say well maybe only the attractors
themselves are experienced however
importantly ineffability exists
regardless in this case right if only a
is conscious
a can still encode the fact that there's
information lost during processing and
working memory during these trajectories
information loss is something that is
computable uh it could be encoded along
some dimensions in the attractor for
instance which explains how you know we
could be consciously aware that there's
information lost during working memory
processing
okay
yeah
um so now I'm going to talk about
generalizing ineffability
um once you view enough ability as
information loss from a source variable
to a destination variable Then There are
a myriad of different Pathways that you
can characterize which we're going to
split into two groups
um so Pathways confined within an
individual or intrapersonal
communication and Pathways that extend
between individuals or interpersonal
communication so in the intra case
you've already seen conscious experience
the working memory trajectory the
attractive State and the message
um but you can also consider D which is
the input data to the system and V which
we use to denote the state of processes
considered
um outside the limitation of working
memory
um and uh you can also consider the
cognitive parameters of the individual
being communicated to so we're going to
work with Alice and Bob
um and we're going to assume that Bob
has a brain which is structurally
identical to Alice's
um but has different parameters uh Phi
tilde instead of Phi and we're going to
denote Bob's
um cognitive State using the tilde
uh so empirical evidence from
Neuroscience suggests that the brain is
hierarchical in nature and there are
many levels of organization many
instances of attractor Dynamics across
organizational levels and cortical
regions
um so one example is the inferior
temporal cortex
um is a sensory processing area that
responds discriminatively to novel
sensory stimuli whereas the pre
prefrontal cortex or PFC appears to be
implicated in maintaining the attention
modulated representations of working
memory
and to a first approximation
um in this simple model it's easy to
obtain the results that richness of one
process constrains the richness of
another
uh so here we have that richness of
working memory trajectories
um HX
um is is upper bounded by the richness
of its inputs and subsequently uh we
also have that the richness of conscious
experience HS is upper bounded by the
richness of conscious experience and the
richness of um sub-process States
now we're going to zoom out and consider
the interpersonal communication case
um Shannon entropy has some drawbacks
when it comes to characterizing
interpersonal ineffability
um a major one is that Shannon entropy
assumes you have access to Phi
um Alice's cognitive parameters uh so
note that H Phi s given M for example is
the descriptional
um uh complexity of us given not just a
but also Phi
um and since we can't assume in the
interpersonal case that Bob has access
to Alice's brain parameters we're going
to rely on the colgoma framework for
information Theory uh if you're
unfamiliar with the congomorov
complexity the first thing to note is
that Congo of complexity or k x is
defined on instances
um X hence the lower case rather than
variables
um we try to notice by capitals
um KX is roughly defined as the length
in bits LZ of the shortest binary
program said that Prince X and holds
um so there's no explicit dependency on
the probability distribution over X
unlike in um Shannon information
uh but we can introduce PS
um by taking an expectation over the
clock complexity of States
um to uh obtain the congomorov version
of Shannon entropy
and likewise for ineffability
um
we characterized it before using
conditional entropy
um in the kogoma framework expected K of
x given y
um is is sort of the analog to Shannon
conditional entropy and that represents
the length of the shortest program that
Prince x given that you know why or that
Y is
um accessible to your program
uh and it's uh approximately equivalent
up to logarithmic terms
um to KX minus i x colon Y where I X
codon Y is called more of mutual
information which can be interpreted as
uh the difference in program lengths for
printing X depending on if you know why
or not roughly speaking
um there are a lot of similarities
between Shannon information and program
information for example
um Mutual information in both cases is
maximized if x is equal to Y uh in the
Shannon case because that means y
uniquely determines X and in the
kokomorov case because it means that
given y
um you don't require any extra bits to
print X
um
in fact uh if you assume knowledge of
the probability distribution p uh then
expected more of complexity and
um
Shannon entropy are equivalent up to
some constant Factor because it turns
out that the most efficient way to
describe a state X on average given that
you know the distribution
um is to encode x with a a description
of length minus log p x bits
um but if you don't know the
distribution
um which we want to make use of uh in in
the interpersonal case because the
parameters of the speaker's brain are
not given
um then the higher the descriptive
complexity of that unknown distribution
then the higher the ceiling on the
difference between expected colgoma of
complexity and Shannon entropy
um uh and in our case we'd expect that
to apply because the space of cognitive
States is enormous the probability
distribution over those States is very
complex and the states themselves are in
general
um complex to reconstruct
um being very high dimensional vectors
um the second advantage of coconut
complexity
um in addition to allowing us to
explicitly avoid conditioning on the
probability distribution is that Shannon
entropy is a measure of statistical
determinability of States as opposed to
difference in unique states
um so in Shannon information
um uh entropy is fully determined by the
probability distribution on States and
it's unrelated to the meaning or
structure or content of the states
um whereas complexity is concerned with
the difficulty of reconstructing
um uh States I.E absolute difference
which corresponds more closely to the
lay definition of ineffability
um here are a number of results that
that we include in the paper so the
first one is quite simple
um uh you can't increase colgoma of
complexity by conditioning on more
States because the program can simply
choose to ignore the input if it doesn't
help to shorten the length of the
program
um so we have trivially that KS given M
the complexity of conscious experience
given the message is at least as great
as K as given M and P Phi
um but you would expect this Gap to be
quite significant uh because of the
complexity of
um P5
um so because in in our case and
generally in non-toy cases
um the probability distribution itself
provides a lot of information so it it
it it significantly reduces the
descriptive complexity of s if you're
able to
um conditional notes
um
this bus results illustrates uh
essentially the difference in
ineffability from the tabular rasa case
on the left where you don't condition on
um Alice's brain parameters Phi
um uh uh to the case where you can
assume access to Alice's uh brain
parameters which is analogous to the
Shannon entropy
um
uh characterization that that
Eric was talking about
but the quantity that we're more
interested in
um is uh this expression in the green
box so K as given M and P tilde Phi
which is the ineffability expected
ineffability
um well in expectation
um of alistair's experience s given the
message and Bob's brain parameters uh
tildify
um you can show that this quantity is up
a bounded
um by an expression that scales with k p
Phi given tilde Phi
um which is a measure of the cognitive
dissimilarity
or the descriptive complexity of Alice's
um brain given Bob's brain
um so in other words if your experiences
are ineffable to someone
I.E the the left hand term in the green
box is is High
um that implies that your brains are
highly behaviorally dissimilar
under our model
um so we can use this this result to
provide an account for what Mary learned
when she stepped out of her black and
white room
uh and essentially
um uh what it's saying is that
neurotypical Alice's experience of color
is ineffable to marry
um uh
which implies that they are cognitively
dissimilar and cognitive dissimilarity
is not the same as knowledge inadequacy
because
um knowing how the brain should respond
to a particular stimulus is not the same
as being able to execute that response
when you're actually exposed to the
stimulus
um so the cognitive dissimilarity
um principle is something that we
generally believe intuitively but it's
also been studied
um in Neuroscience uh so the ability for
the neural neural activity of two brains
to synchronize which is to say to behave
in a mutually determined manner appears
to facilitate communication between
individuals
uh there's also a connection to theory
of mind which is the skill of being able
to infer the thoughts of others so if
Bob's cognitive functions
um uh FX and Fs which produce his
working memory trajectory and his
conscious experience are optimized for
decoding
um Alice's message M into her conscious
experience s then ineffability is
reduced if
um uh Bob's conscious experience as
tilde is conditioned on compared to um
um because
uh it implies that part of the
computation of reconstructing
um s is executed during inference of
tilde s
um meaning that the smallest program
from uh tilde s Bob's conscious
experience
um until defy Bob's cognitive parameters
to
um s Alice's conscious experience would
make use of um tilde s to reduce the
sort of residual work that that needs to
be um uh uh
uh
the residual information that needs to
be supplied in order to determine s
which would shorten the descriptive
length of that program
so in other words making progress at
inferring the conscious experience of
others
um in your own cognitive processing
could literally be interpreted as
reducing the ineffability of their
conscious experience
quickly uh we're going to touch on the
grounding problem um so as Eric
mentioned before two individuals will
generally understand the same word or
sentence in different ways and our
measure of ineffability does capture
this
um dissonance for for two reasons
um and first uh measures of ineffability
um such as we saw uh in the previous
slide
um they uh they are bound by sealing
that scales with cognitive dissimilarity
um or the colgoma of complexity of P5
given P tilde Phi
um and uh Phi includes all the
parameters in Alice's computational
graph including those that parameterize
functions are defined on the input data
D and likewise for Bob so that that
means that
um
uh uh Alice's is uh parameters Phi are
are grounded in a representation that is
at least partly shared with Bob's
tildify so if Bob's parameters Implement
a function that operates differently on
input data
um compared to Alice then they do not
inform on each other to a great uh
extent and the ceiling on ineffability
is is increased via this um KP uh Phi
given P tilde Phi tan and secondly
um conscious experience s uh is a
function of Phi it's computed
um uh using a function that depends on
Phi
um and likewise for Bob
um and and Phi contains Alice's
long-term knowledge therefore
um s is capable of containing uh
information about the associations that
that Alice makes in the process of
generating her her conscious experience
um and and that's included in the
Reconstruction targets of
um k s uh which is to say
um the description of complexity of her
conscious experience
um so our model offers an interpretation
for
um uh the observations of spelling which
remained in 1960 in this very famous
experiment where he showed subjects a
grid of characters
um briefly and then ask them to recall a
specific row
um he observed that uh subjects were
generally able to report the um prompted
row accurately uh but
um not all the characters in The Grid uh
despite being able to report that they
had a conscious experience of
um they sort of had had they consciously
apprehended all uh characters in The
Grid
um and
um our our model uh uh offers an account
for this this phenomenon in in the
following way so
um
upon being exposed to the grid of
characters and being prompted to report
the characters in a specific row
um working memory uh contents
represented by the attractive State a
um presumably contains the identities of
those four characters in The prompted
row as well as a summary over the grid
for example the approximate number of
characters or their Arrangement and an
estimate of the information lost uh by
that that summary
whilst information is sufficient to
discriminate all characters
um would exist at some point in the
computational pipeline
um but uh primarily in Upstream sensory
State uh v
um from which uh working memory
trajectory acts and
um working memory output a are computed
um subsequently since the attractive
State a is directly accessible to to
verbal reporting processes
um the characters of the prompted Row
The Grid details at summary level and
the presence of information loss would
be directly reportable whereas full grid
details uh wouldn't
um and and note that this uh explanation
would hold irrespective of whether you
um where the distinction between
conscious and unconscious is drawn
um so whether X the working memory
trajectory which may contain sufficient
information uh to discriminate all
characters or not
um whether X is considered conscious or
not
um so as this uh suggests
um
one of the points that we make is that
at least when it comes to characterizing
richness and ineffability the exact
definition of
um what constitutes conscious experience
so the definition of FS Phi um in the
computational pipeline
um does it is is not that important
um
we utilize this minimal computational
model
um without relying on the Implement
implementation details in order to allow
us to to to make General statements
about richness and affability
um and as Eric hinted before
um you can account for the report of
ineffable ineffable uh the report of
ineffability
um uh from this computational assuming
this computational graph irrespective of
how you define uh FS
um so if x is considered to be conscious
then the attractor Dynamics bottleneck
the amount of information accessible to
working memory output and verbal reports
but if X is not conscious then
information lost during processing can
still be reported on it can still be
approximately computed and reported on
leading us to reports
on ineffability
um so finally uh some some future
directions for this work uh one of them
is to uh link it to the Neuroscience
um so for example to
um uh
uh actually get some empirical estimates
of the amount of information loss
um using neural correlates of working
memory state for example
um and uh also
um
I think for a deeper understanding of
Consciousness you have to consider why
it exists and not just how it manifests
so this is something that we don't touch
on on the paper
um but
um
uh the use of information bottlenecks in
machine learning would suggest that
information loss actually has a purpose
and specifically the purpose is
generalization
um it's it's improves the robustness of
functions learned from data
uh to noise
um and it improves the ability of of
functions to
um uh
perform
um obviously optimally on inputs that
were not seen during training which is
what what generalization is defined by
um
and uh this is important because if we
want to incorporate
um sort of observations about
Consciousness into our artificial models
what we really want to capture is the
benefit that Consciousness affords
biological models
um and we might not need to transfer the
actual
um form that it takes
in um human cognition
and that's it
awesome thank you for the presentation
it would be awesome if you could give
some opening remarks and then we can
have a discussion and hear any questions
from the live chat
sure well thanks again for the
invitation to uh mind jazz on these
beautiful topics
so as opening questions and discourse I
would say like
uh a strong message here is that uh
through uh the formalization that was
just presented
we have um
an account that allowed to to make the
bridge between access Consciousness and
phonological Consciousness and uh
something that was described very well
in in the paper that was cited uh of
Jonah nakash in philosophical
transaction B how you can you don't
necessarily need something more than
access Consciousness to a campar is
phenomenal aspects
um
but it also let a lot of open questions
like typically
uh we have seen how there is an
information loss within a brain and
between brains but we can also
complexify
uh the the Witten brain uh message
passage for instance adding
metacognition so at media we are also
working on uh
architecture on top of global neural
workspace uh with typically attention
schema Theory from Michael Graziano
and so there is a again in this meta or
presentational steps a lot of
information as well and I think from
empirical uh point of view at both
behavioral and neurophysiological level
there's also a lot to unpack there on
how our metacognitive uh
uh representation of ourselves is also
an impoverished information from the the
real uh states that occur and underlying
and that connected well with the
the social Dimension uh of the of
Consciousness and here we touch a bit on
that with the unifiability the
interpersonal level
but in the case of the attention schema
there is a very interesting uh reversal
from evolutionary standpoint of why the
brain comes up to to represent
others at first and then we are
recycling the the neural mechanisms to
predict others behavior on ourselves and
like there's a kind of uh
flipping of the traditional narrative in
cognition Neuroscience with Graziano
because the others come first in a way
and self-consciousness become a sort of
a side effect of having to have all the
mechanisms to deal with others and
um you know we don't talk too much about
the representation of the cell but I
think it's a very uh interesting uh pass
uh following this work
then there's also a
something that we didn't discuss too
much but uh we we think about the
trajectory to the attractor and how the
many trajectories can lead to one
attractor
but interestingly from a sequence of
attractor you can recover sort of
a trajectory so like if I have a point a
and point B and point C by having the
sequence IBC I will tend to have a
trajectory that looks alike each time
and so uh it's kind of heading towards
like the Dynamics also of social
interaction and culture uh so typically
cultural adaptive facts like musics or
movies or eliciting stuff from a
subjective experience that seems like uh
Stronger Than Just Words and uh and even
I mean I'm saying stronger than words
but even words are sequences so in a way
there is maybe in the Dynamics of
communication
a little bit of information that is
retrieved by the interpolation of
different discrete states of different
attractors so that's uh it's in the uh
the inequality that we saw so the
inequalities are are there but maybe
that we can play a bit and uh with the
those phenomena to see to what extent we
can
retrieve more information by playing on
those dynamical phenomena uh in
communication
and regarding communication so we talked
about the grounding problem and how the
the message in the attractors are kind
of aligned between people through the
shared statistical environment
uh and I think the the conograph
framework is interesting uh in the sense
of
a generative model of the of the world
that you have to um
to share with others and in a sense uh
I'm working a lot on autism and I'm
interested in neurodiversity uh
the the fact that you have this this
similarity the cognitive dissimilarity
as uh in the uh in the information loss
uh it's also very interesting uh to
interpret our diversity of the
biological level can uh have uh an
impact on how certain people will have
more difficulty to communicate with
others in specifically in a neurotypical
world like we have a society that is
very normative in in design for
neurotypical and so people who are more
outside the the norm and are more nor
diverse would then have more difficulty
to align the genetic model and
communicate with others that's also
something that would be nice to discuss
or to explore later
and finally so uh since we are on the
on the active inference uh live stream
uh I would take the the occasion to to
mention or it could uh connect with with
active in France we didn't really uh uh
talked about the active inference uh
formalism in the paper but uh typically
I'm coming back from a workshop on
computational neurofhinology uh where we
we used uh the the previous work of
Varela on neuroscience and phonology to
try to have a generative passage between
first person and third-person experience
and we discussed during the whole week
our computational model models can be a
third uh constraint to to stabilize this
uh relationship between person and third
person perspective unconsciousness and I
was among the rare people there uh not
completely convinced by active inference
but uh and I I was like trying to argue
about uh the need for plurality
at the formalism level I mean even from
a theoretical perspective and for
plurality in those domain but uh at
least from a formal point of view to to
try to not bet all our eggs in the same
uh basket so to say and here it's a very
nice example how even you can combine
formalism that were mutually exclusive
in the literature so for typically uh
coming more from the embodied cognition
and various
work uh people with embodied cognition
where tends to be more in dynamic or a
System Theory and very opposed to
computationalism and information Theory
here we show in this paper that
information Theory and the energy in
theory can totally work hand in hand so
it's it doesn't mean that we need to
commit to one or two of all formalism
but to maintain this priority I think
it's very important from epistemological
standpoint
and
still the the connection with active
inference that could be interesting and
that's one of the things that I kept
from last week Workshop is how from a
social interaction point of view uh
synchronization and a workload on on
intervene synchronization and those
fundamental synchronization can uh be
optimality for information transfer as
we see here but in the the context of
active inference it's also the optimal
uh minimizer of free energy because you
have the two generative models that are
perfectly aligned so you don't have
error in your prediction because the
other person become a mirror of your own
gnrt model so that may be also the
some bridges that and predictions that
can show that those different formalisms
are multiple way of looking at the same
thing so yeah
thank you um awesome points so
feel free to discuss if you have any
responses and just take it from there
Eric and shoe or I can ask some
questions or read some comments do you
have any comments on games thoughts
um yeah I think we have some do you have
things to say
um yeah um that was a long list of
comments
um
I I find your comments about the autism
um I'll link really interesting
um because actually that's that's pretty
much directly what the message of the
result is is that
um cognitive dissimilarity
is associated with difficulty in
communicating
um
so yeah
actually the last thing that that you
said
um
about how
um if the communicator and the listeners
brings are uh synchronized or if they're
equal there's no prediction error
um
that that that that that's kind of the
machine learning problem actually as a
whole um I don't know if this is a big
thing but the whole point of machine
learning is to discover the true model
um that you're trying to learn so that
you have no prediction error right
um
so
yeah I mean
um so I'm not an expert on on active
inference by any means
um
uh but one thing that does
make me a bit like apprehensive about it
is that it's so concerned with
prediction
you know the the the
it's generative models are about
reconstruction you know and and
prediction
um whereas
cognition is about survival
um
and prediction is
part of survival obviously I mean you
need to be able to predict you know
um
I don't know uh
not not crashing into a car or something
so that you don't die but but it's it's
actually you know it's it's it's it's
just a part
um
um and more generally
uh the inference of cognitive states in
the brain is not about
discovery of Truth in some sense you
know it's not about
um uh
um
uh
uh coming up with with with uh true
um uh
uh ex model or explanation for some
phenomenon it's it's about
um uh
sort of optimizing for your for your
Fitness
um
so yeah that's something that that
um I don't quite understand uh sort of
what the active inference
perspective on that would be I don't
know if Daniel or you had some some
comments
or not
okay just jump in with active inference
and then I'll leave more comments in the
chat but I think that's a great set of
points
so if I can make one point to
guillaume's First
you spoke about in the presentation the
generalized ineffability
and it reminded me of a few times in
active inference where we're hearing
about generalized synchrony
generalized which means like not
necessarily lockstep or mirror but
mutually information encoding and not
necessarily linearly correlate and and
synchronized like the end state of the
metronomes but there's like complex
information transfer especially in this
multi-scale setting
um generalized synchrony which is
enabled by the general generalized
coordinates which are the coordinates of
motion of the path so these are kind of
the summary statistics to describe the
Taylor series expansion around that path
or to better describe that path
taken in some way and generalized
homeostasis which for certain
environmental regularities it may be
sufficient to be entirely retroductive
or there may be
physical or cyber physical constraints
so that you'll have a system that is
purely designed a different way so
I wouldn't say any theory is necessarily
too
opinionated with respect to what you
could describe and I think part of the
reason to want such a descriptive
approach which is what I feel like you
all did by deciding to describe an
analytics framework for ineffability
rather than for example a mechanistic
explanation but describing some
evidence
all of that was just to say pluralism in
what we're approaching that ineffable
space from multiple compressions or
bulls to even describe
English words scientific models and it
reminds me of the recent discussions
with Lance DeCosta who described how
other discrepancy measures other than
free energy could be used and that free
energy has been used in machine learning
the variational autoencoders all kinds
of Bayesian applications because it has
a KL diversions and so it has some
convenient variational optimization
properties as a discrepancy measure but
it is not the only discrepancy measure
and you mentioned to in your discussion
which were the Shannon syntactic
sort of classical information content
and then the colomogorov the program and
so that is like another distance measure
so
in some ways these spaces can't or won't
or don't even need to collapse below
pluralism of at least several relatively
stabilized kinds
but I thought that was a very important
Point Guillaume about explanatory
pluralism and how we can be excited
about one area of science or one way of
knowing
and it's compatible with others ways of
knowing because we have some of those
properties of differences that were
discussed
so those are first thoughts before even
any octave technicality
go for it sure no I just remember Mark
that was I mean KL is distance between
two distributions
um
yeah
whereas uh yeah
but anyway yeah get on continue
yeah I was just saying like for in the
case of
the
autism uh this typically show our also
you don't necessarily need to go to the
mechanistic nor biology to have
potential explanation
and so in the in the in the case of
crabber for explaining the brain like
there's a very nice definition very nice
landscape of different kind of
explanation
and uh in the same way like
those different formalism can give
different perspective on how to
understand what's going on uh autism has
been very focused on the neurobiology at
some point and the genetics
but maybe it's not at that level
specifically that the functional
understanding should occur I don't I
don't say it has a no cause are
relationship because it's highly
genetically irritable and so on
but uh sometimes the the functional
understanding is not necessarily at the
uh very uh uh lowest level of uh
explanation here
so now to kind of move to active
inference and really physics based
approaches the trajectory recovery
is going to have some Maximum
information representation with the
generalized coordinates of motion it's
how paths are represented in many
settings
and so that path of least action
the Bayesian mechanics on that landscape
whatever it is
empirically it's like fitting a spline
in that space or doing some other kind
of modeling whether it's SPM modeling or
hyper scanning
there's some kind of generalized time
series modeling
between the present and artifacts the
past the future other entities
what what do you mean Daniel I didn't
get it
just that that kind of trajectory
recovery is what is being parameterized
in
physics of Consciousness type models or
physics of cognition Bayesian physics
anything where a probability
distribution has a position
velocity acceleration and so on it's
being path inferred
continuous time generative models and
there's discrete time generative models
in active
and Hybrid models just like other
Bayesian graphs so in the continuous
time setting
where there's a Taylor series expansion
that's trajectory recovery
yeah well I think more generally
um maybe the point is that you could use
um Bayesian Bayesian learning
variational inference to learn a
generative model of these states that
we're referring to right if you had some
kind of data sets
um uh
uh that actually
represents a sample from let's say the
true model
um then you could use variational
inference to to to
um to approximate that model
um
but you don't have to though I mean
there are many generative modeling
techniques in in machine learning um
that don't fall under variational
inference
or read a comment in a question so
yahshua benjio writes Guillaume Dumas
idea about trajectories of consecutive
attractors to recover information about
likely trajectories that lead into each
of these attractors
that are normally lost in working memory
is very cool
and then Shu Eric any relation between
what you talked about and the
compositional properties of conscious
thoughts
yeah I I think so so in terms of
compositionality of conscious thoughts
uh
I think what yahshua is referring to now
is that
um our thoughts kind of compose Concepts
that we already have so something like
uh you know a sentence if I think uh you
know the Fat Cat I'm composing these
these mental Concepts to fat and Cat and
that generates sort of a a new
experience so experiences are always
generated from these these building
blocks
um and then similarly one thing that we
didn't we didn't talk so much about
is that
conscious experiences language and
attractors can also have this shared
compositional structure so like language
it's clear you know face face where it's
combined to form new little phrases new
sentences that have a novel meaning in a
systematic way
um how this could happen with the
tractors is
um
well kind of in the most basic case
different dimensions in this High
dimensional State space might converge
to different attractors and so now you
know one attractor that's converged to
is really a composition of attractors
along different dimensions
um so this is a sense in which you know
our experiences are compositional uh our
tractors that generate those experiences
um can have compositional structure and
this could be a reason why language
itself is compositional we're basically
trying to come up with some some way of
describing or identifying compositions
of attractors I mean I I would I would
ask that
um
compositionality is a mechanism for
reducing description complexity
so
um you know if in fact that that's
arguably the objective
um
for the compositional nature of our
thoughts and language
um uh you know features like less time
to describe more robustness to noise
um
yeah I mean if you're trying to describe
um an instance of a state
um obviously the description complexity
is much less if it's built up of
Concepts that you you already know about
um
yeah just just to bring this back to
something I mentioned in the talk
um you know I I pointed out that
attractors have this discrete structure
there's a finite number of them and we
could assign labels to them uh but if
these attractors are compositional which
would allow for richer space Richard
number of attractors basically it's
finite but it's the space of total
attractors is exponentially large right
so we don't want a language that's
assigning one unique word to every
composition of attractors it would be an
exponentially large language
um we want some kind of uh language that
will minimize the description like with
what shoe said you know you could have a
language that's compositional
yeah
I think that provides a really I think
you're muted Daniel
sorry
it provides a very
interesting and justific justifying
rationale for using the description
length as opposed to the KL Divergence
which is maybe in some telepathy enabled
world or space
the KL Divergence does help you
move quickly
or on some defined manifold but
in an encoding decoding space
and on the computers that we have
then writing shorter
programs
and or making smaller information
theoretic compressions
becomes
one of the imperatives
to take the kind of empirical approach
that you are describing because though
you've described mainly equations
these are all also computer packages
that can be used to model different data
sets so what kinds of data sets do you
think this is most proximally applicable
to
understand the question yeah are you are
you saying like what kind of data sets
would um
kind of minimum description length the
compositional models be most useful for
or just with the approaches and measures
that you described today what kinds of
data sets or behavioral and cognitive
settings do you think that could be used
as an empirical tool or measure for I
think it'd be really interesting to like
hear about does the data already exist
is it some hypothetical measurement are
there ways to even re-analyze yeah skill
or anyone else
yeah uh I think like uh on language
already there is like a lot of things
that have been done on uh the number of
uh bytes per second transferred for
instance and uh I guess like on large
Corpus of discussions
uh or even in clinical settings for
instance I'm working on uh the the
clinical alliance between a patient and
a clinician for instance this formalism
of unifiability and information loss
would be interesting to apply to as even
a form of
biomarker I mean even if at the language
level is not bio
and then you can also apply those uh
information theoretic measurements to uh
physiological data movement
uh neural data so in my lab we are
recording multiple brains simultaneously
we can totally try to Ampere Achilles
approach what we are describing this
paper uh and and show that for instance
in certain population that are more
challenged to communicate through in our
diversity so what we discussed earlier
uh we can apply the same type of
measurements
with information Theory instead of just
a classical uh no Imaging measurements
so that's that would be for instance a
empirical uh way of dealing with that
what I'm very interested in would be to
make the relationship between the access
Consciousness and the V basically a
process and the information loss that
you have in your working memory
right now the I feel that the no imaging
technology are not at that level of uh
possibility but who knows maybe we're
gonna have a soon the ability to
disentangle that kind of stuff yeah
oh yes yeah so
um
yeah so the delimitation of what
constitutes working memory
um in the brain
um
I think that's that's not a a settled
question right
um I mean there are like lots of
different
um
possible approaches
yeah I mean it's totally up in the air
like uh classically in global workspace
Theory they traditionally thought okay
working memory is localized to
um
cortex now the the New Perspective is
emerging that okay maybe working memory
is sort of distributed uh across the
brain we see kind of sustained attractor
representations uh all over the place in
this distributed working memory so all
these different pieces
um you know what what does what
constitutes x what constitutes that
working memory trajectory
um and and also you know what
constitutes The Experience what's the
function that goes from X from working
memory to an experience uh all that is
is up in the air when writing this paper
we had plenty of discussions about you
know what is the trajectory the whole
trajectory of conscious is just the
attractor conscious as their kind of
sense in which both these things are
true so like Guillaume was talking about
access versus phenomenal Consciousness
uh access Consciousness refers to you
know what I'm what I'm able to report
whereas phenomenal Consciousness kind of
refers more to the the standard
definition of you know what is my
experience like
um so our framework uh kind of
illustrates that well maybe we can unify
these things where X is a trajectory is
some phenomenal experience it's it's in
the moment whereas your attractor is
really the only thing you're able to
report
um remember and you some must still know
that you know something something is
missing between what you're reporting
and what you were actually experiencing
throughout
yeah I mean I think the I mean in in
terms of our model is pretty clear
um but I think
um actually actually grounding it in
empirical uh data sets
um
is is is a challenging question the
other thing is that cognore of
complexity is more of a theoretical
measure
um so that that's actually I think the
reason why Shannon information is much
more ubiquitous
um uh for example in machine learning
um
uh because basically given the
generative model you can you can
approximate it
um for example just using Monte Carlo
um estimation but complexity
um
yeah it would be much more of an
approximation with a much greater um
error I think if you you attempted to to
approximate that
um
so I guess that would be a potential
concern yeah one one advantage of it if
you if you could measure the columnarok
complexity is it would allow you to kind
of measure the um
the ineffability of an experience on an
individual uh case uh so for instance
like one one thing we spoke about with
theory of Mind was that this complexity
of the experience given the message uh
we would think it would be much higher
than an experience given you know Bob's
experience given the listeners
experience because the listener's brain
is doing a lot of the work of decoding
the message into a similar sort of
experience so it'd be useful if you
could see something like are there
certain types of experiences where the
message just wildly and insufficient you
know the the comograph complexity of the
experience given the message is massive
uh but actually people do a really good
job inferring The Experience
um and maybe it would be different in a
case of like autism maybe there's some
sorts of experiences that they simply
can't reconstruct so I think there's
some value in trying to
create measures of comograph complexity
to kind of handle these individual cases
the issue is is yeah it's not really
computable you can't search through the
space of all possible programs but maybe
there are kind of ways to get around
this for instance you could sort of
parameterize a program with
I don't know a neural network let's say
you have neural network going from
message to some some brain scan uh for
an experience and then maybe the size of
that neural network or the complexity of
the network could be
um sort of the
a surrogate for uh the complexity of the
program the shortest program yeah
that's a cool idea
that is really cool it reminds me of
using
adversarial neural networks which don't
have as strong
analytical guarantees as for example
cryptography but then they kind of
converge in being able to protect or
change or modify information in certain
ways
but you aren't getting the same
bounds or guarantees on the formality
and that's kind of like the discrete
continuous
dialectic
and so it's important to embody even
that pluralism with respect to State
spaces because of the formalisms in in
any of these domains the formalism for
discrete in continuous they're not
always aligned and those are definitely
the areas that can be studied
but for the space of empirical models
that we're talking about
as part of even then methodological
pluralism and science but if we're
talking about statistical models we want
to be able to intake the data at some
point so it has to
have certain properties
which are even looser than the math and
there's probably a lot that could fit in
this and I think it'll be interesting
like when you have a hyperscanning
experiment
how do you include the environments or
how do you deal with different
number of sensors or different types of
sensors different kinds of action and
report that people
might encode their symbols through
symbol
all kinds of accessibility
and interface
types which I think returns to the
album's point so yes please
yeah actually that's also uh remind me
that there is also a nice uh empirical
playground and see with what we
discussed is how we can maximize from
environmental perspective instead of the
biological perspective this information
transfer so I'm working for instance
with Michael lip sheets which part of
Arius as well on from anthropological
standpoint humans came out with uh
rituals or cultural practice to to
maximize uh the alignments of people
and those things also are uh very
important in our society or to reach
consensus and collaborate and so on and
uh I guess like
this can also of uh
issue would be a very important I mean
when we have to uh convert on optimal
Collective Dynamics here we are talking
with Alice and Bob in a diadic scale but
a nice follow-up also on this work will
be at the group level how how you
optimize consensus and collaboration on
on group skills particularly for
attacking climate change or social
inequality and very challenging topics
of society
yeah
um yeah so actually that touches on uh a
um
well possibly weakness of of the simple
model that we use which is that we don't
incorporate any feedback loops so we
have this very simple
um unidirectional
model which I think has advantages
because
uh as well because it it sort of shows
basic principles in a very in a
relatively easy to understand way
um but you're right in that
uh realistically there's always feedback
not just at the interpersonal level but
obviously within the brain you know
working memory is is top down
um attention actually so that's that's
something that we didn't address in this
in this yeah it would be really
interesting to sort of unify our work
with the the field of pragmatics which
is exactly about this of like you know
given many back and forth
um
uh steps in dialogue how do people come
to a consensus you know and and this
could also uh kind of involve the active
inference framework where you know as a
listener I'm going to ask questions that
are going to try and reduce my uh my
uncertainty about the speaker's State as
much as possible
awesome thank you for these comments so
in my experience
computer scientists and those who have
empirical data measurement experience
they know that you can have different
kinds of Behavioral measurements or just
columns in a database you could have
heart rate and you can have video data
and you can kind of have this like
open-ended it doesn't need to be just a
matrix that gets multiplied in this
extremely clean way and I feel like that
leads a lot of these
very open-ended and flexible approaches
which on one hand address the different
forms and functions and settings
that these kinds of questions are asked
and like at the same time are
working
if not to address at least to have
continuity with classical discussions
on a wide range of topics like sequence
yeah the the question of you know not
everything is a vector not everything is
a matrix you could have more complicated
data structures
um that's really interesting I think
relevance to
Consciousness so it certainly seems like
our thoughts uh our experiences have
this sort of symbolic structure in a way
right you can kind of think of them as
like any thought sort of a graph I have
a couple Concepts in mind maybe in
working memory and and I have some idea
of how they they relate to each other
you know if it's not a graph it's it's
something like that maybe some kind of
smooth representation of a graph
um on the audio on the other hand when
you just look at the brain all you see
is neurons all you see is this
distributed high-dimensional neural
activity so there's this really
interesting question of of uh
how how you link them together and uh I
think attractor Dynamics are another uh
interesting Avenue for for getting Eric
and you could you kind of get a lot of
things you get these these high
dimensional continuous states that you
could represent
um you get sort of discrete states that
you could represent and they could
compose together so um yeah I I I think
there's there's a there's something
there
to kind of
extend that point
to this very meta science area of
discussion around pluralism in science
that Guillaume open the the
um box on
when practice in the behavioral lab if
not much more broadly is using
structures that have different column
types
than certain kinds of
decisions that might have been taken to
be in principle or like Arguments for
the superiority even contextually of one
framework those are just
unveiled purely methodologically as
modeler degrees of freedom like whether
you use a generative
model that's continuous time or discrete
time continuous State space discrete
State space the thermometer data how you
discretized it where you put the
thermometer
all these broader factors that kind of
instantiate the experiment in the
pipeline
they're just all embodied and cultured
Niche events in a scientific niche in a
social niche
and that's a very
pragmatic
or
people might use other words or like
realist
or I don't know what adjective would
describe that take on starting with the
scientific community and formal modeling
and the modeling process as its own
behavioral object
and then working so
have the empirical practice
more General like leading the generality
open-endedness with practice
though that raises so many second order
questions as well
yeah well we can have also from a very
pragmatic standpoint like we need to
have our producibility so to have like
those uh
Norms in design of experiment and formal
uh tools
makes sense but we need to just remind
ourselves often that they also constrain
our way of thinking and typically uh
uh the the story of science shows our
mathematics uh is Guided by the problems
that we have to solve uh and typically
if we take a quantum mechanics uh it was
not like the formalism was popped out at
first and then uh Quantum physicists use
it it's like it was a generative process
and a collaborative effort between
mathematician and physicists and
interestingly they come up even with two
different formalism that were shown to
be compatible later on so it's a nice
tales in a way showing how you can have
even a stronger industrial objective
consensus by adopting different
formalism that then later on are shown
to be uh compatible and and equivalent
so
and here I I have unfortunately to to
live at some point to pick up my
daughter but uh we can go into category
Theory and more meta mathematics to to
to try to show that those four majors
them in the end are potentially uh
equivalent but
from a history of science I think it's
not just about the equivalences also to
have different viewpoints that confirm
each other uh to make a uh our idea our
model of the world uh interceptively
stable
so to say
yeah
I'll give you a small short closing
comic yum and then we'll talk a little
bit more soon Eric
um when I first saw some of your figures
for hyperscanning and there were nodes
that were being connected with different
edges that were within and among brains
and there was this one part slash
dimension of my experience that was like
you can't do that they're not connected
it's like
but it's a statistical causal graph so
it they are exactly the same type of
explanation in empirical data structure
it's the same exact Mutual information
linear causation whatever you want to do
in edges and Edge in that representation
and that's the map territory situation
they're not the ones that are touching
and it was just like by seeing two
levels and the way that the
representation could be used
it was approved by example what it meant
at one level
yeah
well it was hard to uh to publish at
first because I think of that uh reason
yeah
thank you very much
thanks again for the invitation take
care
so what direction would you like to go
or I can read another comment or anyone
else in the live chat in our last minute
okay let's um kind of uh read last
comment from Joshua wrote
but these attractors presumably
correspond to different concepts in the
same sentence are not independently
sampled sorry it's not like verbatim but
what are these structures in language
in terms of like I thought that was very
memorable
um thing to say that words are sequences
to
it's like they're modular with respect
to the dictionary but then even the
phonemes or the the writing structures
have their own
compositional logic like a periodic
table and then there's sub logics
and then there's just different uses of
different levels of description
which is why we don't speak the same
language
unless we do
yeah well directly I think what Josh was
uh referring to is like that when you
when you sample a sentence I guess like
clearly these are their own discreet
things but you're not going to be
sampling them independently from each
other it's like different words we'll go
here more or less and also they're
they'll cohere more or less given a
context right you want to form some kind
of sentence that describes some some
contextures and observations so uh yeah
in regards to these these compositional
attractors again just a simple picture
where you have different attractors
converging along different dimensions
um obviously these These attractors are
going to affect the convergence of
others right so it's not like everything
is just moving independently along
different dimensions
um yeah yeah I mean um simplifying
assumption that we make in a simple
computational model used in the paper
um is that we hide uh sort of
dependencies as noise
um in the variables to avoid uh needing
to consider these these links explicitly
um to sort of highlight the main
um points about richness and affability
that that we wanted to make
um
but I really liked your point
um Daniel about how
um
there is uh sort of the data there's the
physical reality and then there's the
compositional structure that is sort of
imposed on that I mean it's it's a model
right so it's a modeling assumption that
you make
um and you have to choose
uh
at what level of abstraction
um to to Define that model and it can
feel a bit arbitrary
um
yeah and then you you also you also
discussed kind of uh yeah well we all
speak different different languages
um yeah an interesting question for that
in in our work is
um
well okay was it would that imply that
we have different attractor structures
across different cultures that have
different languages is there an
interaction there
um or are these just you know these
different languages equivalent ways of
described in the same state of
attractors and I think you know it's
it's it's somewhere in the middle uh
regardless of what language we'll I
think similar Concepts in similar
conscious experiences
uh but there's there's some kind of uh
cases where you know you have a word in
a given language that uh maybe
identifies sort of a fundamental
attractor and that's kind of like
they're part of their their
conscious vocabulary I guess whereas you
know we regardless of what language we
speak we'd be able to you know get in
that conscious State ourselves but
maybe given our language like the
attractors that you would need to
compose to to construct this conscious
state would would be a bit more
complicated you know you'd need like
something like a longer a longer
sentence a longer thoughts uh to to have
the same sort of experience
awesome well one thing that
brought to mind was
neural patches on the skin like
different parts of the body have
different density of sensory types
from very fine scale touch and actuation
to some more broader patches like where
two needles you can't determine the
difference between them
and then that relates to
many areas to kind of development of
taste and differentiability being able
to to determine differences
and then you
um
of course use this very like evocative
but also grounded
dual representation of the samples
that are discrete and may have
compositional structure with a path
that's moving through them and seeking
to embed the topology of the
sample points within a information
geometry which is the kind that our
actual statistics input and then the
neural patches are regions where to one
person it's like yeah I drove through
New Mexico and to the other person it's
like
every inch they're having this Rich
experience they know the different stops
and then I think one last grade point
from the presentation was
um that we could kind of I'm not exactly
sure I've said but emulate this
informational characteristic
and maybe not even
have that the embodiment for that to
even have consciousness of course
that'll be the debate then
but the debate used to be much less
sophisticated than that and also people
took principal stances
yeah
I wasn't totally clear on that that last
point that you uh that you made
principled stances on whether this would
be emulating or simulating or
approximating analytical framework for
consciousness
or whether this by implementing that
machine
that it would be implementing
Consciousness versus like the kind of
linear regression package that does
cognitive modeling that could be
understood in a purely SPM like
framework and SPM
doesn't
take a package perspective except maybe
implicitly on like whether SPM models
generate consciousness
most likely it's easy to say no because
of generalized linear models so some
people may take an in-princible stance
that any description or simulation on in
certain ways
it's all good we're definitely not
generating anything conscious it's just
would purely be a hugely energetically
expensive potentially
statistics exercise
which is fine
yeah so I mean I mean the the the chain
of reasoning of all work
um I suppose is that if you assume
um a certain model of Consciousness then
that implies ineffability as it is
understood by information loss but
obviously information loss does not
apply it does not imply consciousness
um even though it's an attribute
um of of how Consciousness manifests
um in humans
um
so
yeah I mean this this question of of
um
what is the necessary this is a rata to
to declare whether a system is conscious
or not is sort of very
uh
it is not you know what we discuss in
the paper at all
um
I mean from my perspective as as a
machine learning practitioner
um it's it's it's closer to what I said
in the last slide I would like to get
the benefits of consciousness
in in an artificial model and it it
doesn't matter so much
whether the form that takes
um is similar to how it manifests in in
biological
um systems or not why should it
you know I mean we don't have the kind
of resources that
um Evolution has had over over you know
a billion years to to optimize support
for this for this model
um so the question is
you know how do we design how do we
Design Systems that that can benefit
from for example the generalization and
robustness properties
um that being very contractive in
processing can give you a rather than
you know what's the exact definition for
Consciousness and how do we replicate
that that inner machines because that to
me is sort of a very superficial
um
um uh well it's a it's a more
superficial problem in that it's looking
at the how and not the why
yeah yeah I have some thoughts on this
also so I mean
um Jonathan Simon who's who's a
co-author uh on on our work
um he gave a really interesting
presentation recently there which is you
know whatever model of Consciousness you
assume let's say Global workspace Theory
um there's a minimal model of it that
you could construct right like we we
could easily construct some kind of uh
model like to make this really concrete
there's a bunch of mini neural networks
that are the sub processes and they're
they're communicating uh through some
like shared RNN let's say so you could
construct the minimal model like this
train on some tasks and then you know if
if your your Viewpoint was that a global
workspace Theory with such and such
properties
um is what generates Consciousness well
then you'd be forced to say that your
your minimal model
um is conscious
and this is
in a way
I guess not problematic but but sort of
counter-intuitive because the model
could be doing really simple things they
could not even be reporting that it's
having any Consciousness at all it might
not even have language it might just be
doing something like solving mnists in a
global workspace type architecture but
do you really want to say that that
thing is uh is is conscious
um so uh yeah it is a
a problem I think with uh most series of
Consciousness uh maybe one kind of uh
exception in my view is theories that
say
um
you know we basically have a
representation that we're conscious so
um one canonical example I guess is uh
Michael Graziano's attention schema
Theory
um which basically says
um our brain constructs a model of uh
what attention is is doing in the brain
and that model basically just describes
something that is like experience it
describes oh I'm aware of these things
uh the they have they have these these
properties uh you know I could report
that I'm experiencing these things it's
basically a representation a set of
neural activity uh in in the brain and
there um you don't have the same problem
where you can construct a minimal model
because presumably this representation
of Consciousness is uh is really complex
um and then I guess another set of of uh
theories uh would say that even if you
emulate you know whatever processes in
the brain we think generate
Consciousness
um the physical implementation might be
really important over here so the
example that comes to mind is IIT which
would say you know
it's basically uh substrate dependent in
the sense that you could have the exact
same function the exact same mechanism
implemented in in different ways like uh
you know on a on a computer processor or
a neuromorphic hardware and in one case
there there may or may not be the
Consciousness whereas you have the exact
same function in another substrate and
yeah it is conscious so
um that's that's uh I guess uh another
class of theories that would say that
emulation does not necessarily imply
that you're actually generating uh
Consciousness yeah
all in our last two minutes what are
your closing thoughts or next directions
exhortations to the humans and language
models
yeah well I I guess my um
I'm interested in in this stuff a lot
from uh purely philosophical uh
perspective so um you know the hard
problem for me is really Salient of you
know why would any physical mechanisms
generate Consciousness
um and the nice thing at least for for
me about this workbook the the most
satisfying part of it was that you know
I initially had this intuition that
experiences you know what the color red
is it's not just information it's kind
of uh you know under determined there's
something more than just information
because I can't do things like describe
it uh but you know now now we have a
theory that kind of uh
kind of breaks that that intuition and
now I have a satisfying explanation I
feel for you know why I can't describe
my experiences uh but but under a
physicalist framework so I think it'd be
interesting to to reason through some uh
some other of the the thought
experiments that make the heart problem
Salient and kind of
um yeah to develop some some some models
uh that kind of break the intuitions for
for the hard problem uh for in my case
at least like you know I've seen it done
in in this scenario uh with the topic of
ineffability so there's no reason in
principle that it can't be done uh
across other aspects of the hard problem
yeah so I think if I were to sum up the
work
um
in one very high level sentence it's
that um
um
well reasoning subjectively about
subjectivity
is very difficult but reasoning
objective objectively about subjectivity
is easier and that's sort of what we do
in the paper because
um we take an objective standpoint and
we try to
um you know formalize or characterize uh
subjectivity from that standpoint
um
uh since yeah that that sort of makes
makes the picture clearer
um
I mean from my perspective
I'm interested in Consciousness
um
mainly in terms of what it offers what
it brings
um uh in terms of
um
for example improving generalization of
artificial
um land models
um
yeah it's it's interesting because
uh so another work that I'm doing is is
is
um formalizing generalization bounds
um for for information bottleneck um
which is a regularization principle
um used in machine learning so it's just
really interesting how evolution
uh
has has sort of discovered by itself
this this
um uh regularizer principle
um that that that it it's uh applies to
to human cognition
um
foreign
actually does improve
um guarantees on on generalization
um that that is really mind-blowing to
me yeah
um yeah
wow
great presentation
so thank you both for joining you're
welcome back anytime
yeah thanks so much Daniel it was a lot
of fun
are you okay